When I think about stacks, mostly I
would think about the stack data
structure.
But, when you solve more and more
problems, you would begin to realize
that there is actually a coding pattern
by which you can identify that okay, I
need to apply stacks over here.
And that is what we're going to explore
in this video. Hello friends, welcome
back to my channel.
The first thought that comes to my mind
is a stack of plates because that is
really easy to visualize and you can see
the last-in-first-out principle being
applied.
In a cafeteria, all of the plates get
collected and then the plate on the top
is the first one to get washed. So, that
is the basic idea how a stack data
structure looks like. Basically, you
will have some kind of a structure where
you store all of your elements and then
you are supporting some particular
operations. For example, the peek
operation. You are just accessing the
top element but not removing it. Then,
you have the pop operation. You pop out
the element from the stack and then you
want to use it somehow. Next, you have
the push operation. As soon as you do a
push, this element will go on the top of
the stack. And after that, we all know
about the LIFO principle or the
last-in-first-out. The last element that
gets added at the top of the stack, this
is the first element to pop out. This is
the basic ideology how a stack data
structure looks like. Now, more than
just real life, stacks have a very good
example in programming as well. The very
first example that you might have seen
with stacks is valid parentheses. This
is a common problem where you are given
a mathematical expression and you have
to identify if it is even valid or not.
Think about it. If I give you a very
huge mathematical expression, will you
just try to start solving it? What if
the expression is not even valid? You
want that your process is very fast. You
want your program to be efficient. And
for a valid expression, the number of
opening brackets should be equal to the
number of closing parentheses, right?
And they should follow a particular
order.
You cannot have a closing bracket first
and then an opening bracket. This is
invalid.
So, in this particular question, you are
given a set of parentheses in which they
are appearing, and you have to tell me
if this is valid or not.
So, how do you usually go about solving
this problem? The idea over here is that
you take up a stack data structure and
as soon as you get any of the opening
parentheses, you will add it to your
stack. So, for the first example, I add
a opening parenthesis in my stack over
here.
Now, move ahead. I get a closing
parenthesis. Look for the top element of
your stack.
If they are matching and they complement
each other,
for example, this is the opening
bracket, this is the closing bracket.
Everything is good, so I can simply
remove this bracket from my stack. Next,
I see a opening curly brace, so I add
this to my stack.
And then, going forward, I have a
closing brace.
This is the same in the stack, so I can
remove it.
Next, I have a square bracket. And then,
when I move ahead, I have a closing
bracket. I match it and okay. I'm able
to remove this as well.
I have iterated my all the parentheses
and my stack is also empty, so
everything is good. This is a very basic
example.
Let us look at one complicated example
and see what is happening.
You just have to follow the rules that I
just told you.
As soon as you see a opening
parenthesis, just add it to your stack.
Again, you have a opening brace, so add
it to your stack. Next, you have a
opening parenthesis again, so add it to
your stack.
Now, see, you are getting a closing
bracket. Match it to the top element of
your stack. They are complementary,
right? This is closing and this is
opening. So, what you will do is you
will just remove this element. Next, you
have a opening square bracket. So, let
us add it to the stack. You just have to
follow simple rules. Then, you have a
closing bracket. You match it. It
matches. So, I will remove this.
Next, I have a closing curly bracket. It
matches. So, I'm going to remove this as
well. The next element is the opening
curly bracket. I add it again. I have a
closing bracket. So, this gets removed.
And notice, I have the last element of a
closing bracket. I have this in my top
of my stack. So, I will remove it as
well. So, what have I done? I have
traveled my entire expression and my
stack is also empty. That means this
expression was valid. Think about it. If
there had been any other bracket
somewhere in middle. If I had a opening
bracket over here, then what would
happen? I would still have one opening
bracket dangling in my stack over here.
That means my expression is invalid.
So, just by these simple checks, a stack
is helping you to identify if your
expression is valid or not. And this is
one of the most basic use cases that you
would have seen with the stack data
structure. But definitely, as you solve
more and more problems, you will see
more applications of the stack. For
example, the problem min stack.
What is special about a min stack? It
will have all of the same operations as
a stack data structure. You will just
have one additional operation that you
have to implement, get minimum. The idea
over here is that as soon as you call
get minimum, it should return me the
minimum element that I have encountered
up till now.
So, how can you make this happen? If you
have a normal stack, and this is the
input sequence that you're getting.
What will happen? All the numbers will
start coming in. 1 5 -3 and then a 8.
If someone asks you, okay, what is the
minimum element? Then, you cannot just
iterate over a stack. You will have to
pop all the elements, find the minimum,
return them, and then pop them back
again.
This means you are having so many
useless operations.
How can you optimize it? The idea over
here is that you take the help of one
more auxiliary stack. And this stack
will keep a track of every minimum
number that I have found up till now.
So, let us try to go over this again.
I get the first number and this is one.
For now, this is the minimum number, so
I will add it to my min stack. Next, I
have the number five. Add it to your
regular stack. That is fine.
But, check the top of your minimum
stack. Five is greater than one, right?
That means my minimum element will still
be one out of these. So, I do not want
to update it. I will let five live only
here.
The next element is minus three. Add it
over here.
And then, should you add minus three
over here? Yes, because minus three is
even less than one. That means up till
this limit, I have a new minimum.
So, I add minus three here.
Then, next element is eight. So, you
just add it over here.
Next element is minus one, but I still
have a minus three which is even lower.
So, don't add it.
Up till now, everything is good. As soon
as someone says, "Okay, get me the
minimum." Instead of looking in this
stack, look in your min stack. And you
can tell them, "Okay,
minus three is the smallest number up
till now."
And that is how you can make use of a
helper stack.
For example, what happens if I try to
pop from my stack now?
Let us say I do a pop operation, so
minus one gets out. But, at the same
time, you will check your minimum stack
also. Are you popping the same number?
No. So, leave the minimum stack as is.
You pop out the next number and that is
eight. You don't have eight in your min
stack, so let it be. The next number you
pop is minus three. So, you remove this.
But, in your min stack, you have minus
three here as well.
So, you will need to remove minus three
also.
That is how this stack and this stack
will maintain kind of the same state.
If someone asks you, "Give me the
minimum." You will not return -3. You
will return 1 because out of the
remaining elements of the stack, you
have to tell me the minimum.
That is why you will look at both of
these stacks simultaneously and then
perform your operations.
If you have more elements coming in,
let's say 10 comes in, you add a 10 over
here.
Then you have -99 coming, add a -99
here, and then you're going to update
your min stack as well.
That is how you keep on doing it and you
can return the minimum element in just
order of one time.
I know it will take up an extra space of
order of n, but that is fine. We are
compromising on the space for a better
time complexity.
So, what did we do here? We took a
helper stack and that helped us to
achieve our goal.
When you think about stacks, one other
data structure immediately comes to your
mind and that is queue.
A queue follows a first in first out
policy. So, you might have seen a
problem like this. You have to implement
a queue, but you have to use stacks.
Naturally, you cannot make that happen
just by using a single stack.
So, let us assume I am taking one more
helper stack.
And I have to somehow perform these
operations: enqueue, dequeue, and peek.
Peek simply means looking at the top
element.
So, now let us say I am adding some
elements in my queue.
Let us say I add the elements 5 then 8
and then a 16.
What will happen in a queue?
In a queue, 5 will be the first element
to pop out.
But in your stack, what will happen? You
have 5 and then a 8 and then a 16.
If you try to pop, 16 will get out. So,
these are not the same.
This is where your helper stack comes in
handy. When you are enqueuing elements,
just keep them adding to your primary
stack. Don't do anything.
Now, when you have to look at the
dequeue operation, this is what you need
to do. Just follow the rules.
For the DQ operation in a queue, five
will get out, right?
Over here, I have five at the very last.
As soon as you get a DQ,
take up all of these elements and put
them in your helper stack.
So, what will happen? 16 will get here,
eight will get here, and then five will
get here.
Now, what do you do? As soon as someone
says you, "Okay, DQ."
You need to return me an element from
this particular stack. So, five will get
returned.
What did we do? We were able to simulate
a queue using just stacks. Now, let us
say more elements come in. Let us say 23
came in, and then 42 came in.
Remember what I told you. Whenever you
are having NQ operations, just add these
elements to your normal stack.
Now, let us say someone calls DQ.
You will return a eight over here,
right?
But, what do you do this time?
This time, this helper stack is not
empty.
So, you do not want to transfer all of
the elements until your stack is empty.
If someone says DQ, look in your helper
stack. If there are elements, return
this. So, what will happen? Eight gets
out of your queue, and eight gets out of
this particular stack as well.
We are having a one-to-one operation,
correct? If someone says DQ again,
16 will get out of the queue, and 16
will get out of here.
So, we are having a feature parity.
Now, if someone calls a DQ, this time 23
will get out, but your other stack is
now empty. So, first of all, you will
need to pop all of your elements from
the current stack to the helper stack,
and then you pop out an element, and
then 23 will get out, and you will have
maintained the same kind of feature
using two stacks and a queue that you
didn't even have in the first place.
The peek operation is also very, very
similar, and I I you can figure that out
on your own.
So, what are we doing up till now? We
are just exploring some of the basic
applications of a stack. For example, we
are matching parentheses.
Once you are done matching parentheses,
you can also use it to evaluate
expressions. You will just use the same
stack to solve small portions and then
you get your result from it.
Similarly, you can also think about
parsing code.
A code also has brackets, right? And
this is the same as matching your
parentheses.
That is how a compiler knows that okay,
one of the bracket was not matched.
And similarly, you can think about
tracking histories as well.
For example, you have your undo and redo
buttons. What do they do?
The undo button keeps a stack of each of
the operation that you have done.
And when you do an undo,
it will look at the topmost operation
and then it will keep on going down till
you keep clicking back.
Once you're clear with all of this, it
is actually time that you dive into some
of the advanced concepts which are
solved using a stack data structure.
For example, you might have heard of the
problem next greater element.
Basically, you are given this particular
array and you have to tell me the next
greater element for each of these
elements in the array.
What does that mean? For example, when I
look at three,
I will start to traverse and what is the
next greater element I can find? It is
five. So, for my answer, I will write
down a five over here.
For one, what is the next greater
element? It is five again. So, I will
write down a five here.
For five, what is the next greater
element? I keep going, I keep going, I
find a seven.
So, I write down seven here.
For two, what is the next greater
element? It is seven again. So, seven.
For one, I have seven.
For zero, I have seven.
For seven, I have nine.
For nine, I do not have any greater
element. That means I can write down a
minus one over here. It just depends
upon the problem you are solving.
For two, I have the next greater element
as three.
And for three, I don't have anything, so
I can write down a minus one over here.
This is the answer that I'm expecting.
But how do you reach here?
If you have already noticed, for finding
the next greater element, we are always
going from the left towards the right.
And it is certainly possible that you
might have to go all the way to the end
for every element to find out the next
greater element.
So, think about it. What if we start
from the very back and then try to build
upon our solution?
That can maybe give us a small hint and
maybe help to solve efficiently as well.
But how do you get an intuition that I
might need a stack data structure over
here?
Remember that I told you we have to go
from the reverse direction.
And if I will take up a stack and add
all of the elements in a reverse
direction over here,
what will happen? The top most element
will be somewhere over here, right? It
will be the leftmost element.
And think about it. That is what I need
to explore also.
For example, when I look at three, I may
not want to go all the way to the end to
find a nine.
I could have find a next greater element
somewhere earlier.
So, these elements should be somewhere
on the top of the stack.
And all of these elements should be
somewhere at the lower most portion of
the stack.
We are still going to decide how to add
and remove elements from the stack, but
this is the general idea.
So, how do you start?
Let us try to build our output area
again.
What is the first element I see? I see a
three.
My stack is currently empty. That means
I do not have any greater element.
So, what I can do is I can write down a
minus one over here.
And I will add this element to my stack.
So, three gets added to the stack.
Now, go ahead. Look at the next element.
Next element is two.
Check your stack.
Do you find a next greater element over
here?
Yes.
So, what I can do is I can write down
three over here.
This is the next greater element,
correct?
But also,
this two itself,
it might be a next greater element for
some of the previous elements. I don't
know yet because I haven't seen them
yet.
So, I will want to keep it in my stack
also.
So, I will write down two in my stack
over here. Correct?
Look at the next element. The next
element is nine.
Check the top of your stack.
Do you find any greater element?
The top element is two. It is not
greater. So, what I can do is I can
remove this element.
Why?
Because I know that in my stack, I will
have stored all of the greater elements
at the very end.
So, I need to keep popping the elements
until I find a greater element.
And this is why this stack is called a
monotonic stack.
At every instance, I will ensure that
this stack has increasing number of
elements when I keep popping them.
If I pop the next element, that is
three. Three is also less than nine.
So, I will remove this element also.
Now, my stack is empty.
So, I can say that I don't have any
greater element than this.
And I will add this nine to my stack.
Just wait a little while and everything
will become clear.
What is the next element? That is seven.
So, check. Can you find a next greater
element in your stack? Yes, nine is
greater. So, I can write down nine over
here.
Also, what I will do is I will add this
seven to my stack because this seven
could be a next greater element to some
other element that I yet have to see.
Look at the next element. It is a zero.
Check in your stack. Do you find a next
greater element? Yes, I didn't have to
pop. So, I can straight away use this
seven.
So, I write down this seven here.
Also, I will add this zero to my stack.
Notice what is happening. This stack is
always monotonic. It will have elements
in an increasing order every time. And
I'm doing this so I can reach at my
solution.
Look at the next element. It is one.
Check your stack.
Do you find a greater element than one?
No. So, what did we do? Our stack have
all the elements in an increasing order.
So, I know that if I pop elements, I may
find the next greater element over here.
So, I will remove this zero.
Do I find a next greater element? Yes.
So, I will write down a seven over here.
And what I'm going to do is I will add
this one over here.
And once again, we do this because it
might be possible that this one itself
is a next greater element to some other
element that we haven't yet seen.
And your stack is still in an increasing
order.
Notice the next element. That is two.
Do you find a next greater element over
here? No. So, I can remove this.
Do you find a next greater element here?
Yes, that is seven.
So, I can write down a seven over here.
And I will also write down a two in my
stack.
Check out five. Is two the next greater
element? No. So, I will remove this.
Is seven the next greater element? Yes.
So, what I will do is I will write down
seven again.
And this five gets added to the stack.
Notice how our stack is always
monotonic. It is always increasing in
nature.
Now, I have one.
Check the next greater element. Yes, you
can find it. Five. So, no need to worry.
I can simply write down over here.
And at the same time, add this one also
to my stack.
For the next element, you see three. Is
one the next greater element? No,
because one is smaller.
So, I remove this.
Check the next element. Is five greater?
Yes, so I will write down over here.
And that's it. I have traversed my
entire array and I used this monotonic
stack to get my same answer.
If you notice, they both are the same.
So, what are we doing over here?
We took an advantage of the fact that
this stack can hold all the elements in
an increasing order.
And the pop operation is ensuring me
that I get all of these elements one by
one.
Make sure to pause this video right over
here and understand this concept of next
greater element.
This is a very good use case and you
will find a lot of problems that utilize
the same concept in one way or the
other.
And that is what makes monotonic stacks
very, very important to understand.
For example, you might have seen one
more problem on Leadcode and that is
called daily temperatures.
I will now show you how this problem is
very, very similar to finding the next
greater element. Basically, what happens
is you are given a temperatures array.
All of these are representing the
temperature on a certain day.
The temperature on first day is 73, then
74, 75 and so on.
You have to tell me after how many days
will I get a warmer temperature?
So, if I try to just brute force this
problem,
for the first element, after how many
days do I get a hotter temperature?
After just one day. So, I will write
down a one over here.
For the next element, after how many
days do I get a hotter temperature? One
day. So, I will write down one here.
For 75,
after how many days do I get a hotter
temperature? For one,
two, three and then four, because 76 is
greater than 75.
So, I write down four here.
For 71, one, two.
For 69, just one.
For 72, just one again.
For 76, I do not get a hotter
temperature. So, for this particular
problem statement, you have to write
down a zero here.
And then for 73, I again do not get a
hotter temperature. So, once again, I
have to write down a zero.
So, while going through this, what did
you observe? Tell me.
Is this problem anywhere related to
temperatures or getting hotter?
No. All you are doing is you are finding
the next greater element.
For example, for 73, you are finding the
next greater element to be 74. Then once
again, 75. Then once again, 76.
You are finding the next greater
element, right?
But instead of writing the actual value,
you don't have to write 74, 75, and 76
here.
All you have to do is you have to tell
me after how many days do I get that
temperature.
So, what are you doing?
You just need to find out the index
difference between these two things.
So, instead of storing the actual
numbers in your stack,
what you can do is you can also store
the positions of each of the number.
By that, when you are iterating
backwards,
as soon as you find 75 and you find 76,
for this particular problem, 76 will
have a position associated six, and 75
will have a position associated two. So,
6 minus 2 gives you a four.
And that is it. This problem is
literally the same.
If you understand monotonic stacks,
you can solve this problem really
easily.
And monotonic stacks usually work around
the same principle.
Basically, first of all, you initialize
the stack.
Then you will try to scan through all of
your elements.
And then the most important condition is
you have to maintain your monotonicity.
You have to find out how to pop and how
to push elements such that the stack
maintains its state.
You resolve and you find the next
greater elements or the next smaller
elements based upon your condition.
And then you want to update your stack.
This is how we're maintaining the state.
And this loop just goes on.
This is the idea how monotonic stacks
actually work.
And this particular concept is very very
essential. I keep repeating the fact
because I have seen a lot of very hard
problems, but once you have figured out,
"Hey, this is the solution." They become
really really simple to solve.
And I want to take up an example problem
which I have found very hard myself.
Just reading through it, I wasn't sure
what is happening.
And I will try to break it down as much
as possible.
But remember, the underlying idea of a
monotonic stack will still remain the
same. Let us see if you are able to
figure it out. The problem I'm talking
about is called trapping rainwater.
Over here, you are given a certain
array.
And this array is representing the
height of each building.
So, building one has a height of zero,
building two has a height of one, then
zero again, then two, then one, and so
on.
So, basically, if you will try to map
all of these heights on a grid,
you are trying to see a horizontal
section of a city. So, the first
building doesn't have any height. The
next building has a height of one, then
again zero, then a height of two, then a
height of one, then zero,
then one again, and this time you have a
height of three,
then two,
then one, then two, and then one again.
So, you are kind of looking at the
horizon view of a city, right? You might
have seen this kind of a view.
Our city kind of looks like this.
And now what happens? This is it, the
programming part begins.
You have to treat all of these cities or
towers as containers or walls.
And water just came down.
So, basically it started to rain.
And when it rains, what will happen?
Water will get filled up in all of these
places, right?
Notice what will happen at the very end.
Since you do not have any wall here, all
of this water will just flow down,
correct?
And similarly, check out this height.
You do not have any building or any wall
here. So, the water will simply flow
out.
You have to remember these things.
What about this particular section?
You will fill water over here because it
is bounded by two places.
But you cannot get any top because any
water that comes here, it will just
start to flow down.
For this particular section, you will
have a lot of water here and then any
additional water will start to flow down
and it will ultimately flow down over
here.
So, after it has rained,
how much water is trapped?
You are looking at this particular
cross-sectional view.
This is the ultimate amount of water
that will get trapped, correct?
Notice, I cannot have any water over
here. Any water I have here, it will
start to flow down because there is no
wall.
So, it will flow down from here and then
from here.
Similarly, I could not trap any water
here or here. It simply flows down. And
same is the condition for this section
as well.
The only water I have trapped are these
units.
And you have to tell me, given this
array,
how much water have I trapped?
In this particular problem, how much
water did I trap?
I trapped a total of six units. 1 2 3 4
5 and then 6.
So, for this particular test case, six
is your answer.
Now the tricky part. Where do you even
begin solving this problem? There are so
many different ways to approach it.
How do you start to even calculate the
water at a particular place?
To understand it, let us focus on the
very basic concept.
For example, when I'm looking at just
this particular section,
how much water is it going to trap?
You have a wall on the left, and you
have a wall on the right.
You know that you will only trap the
minimum height, because any height
greater than this, the water will just
flow.
This is giving you the height that you
can trap.
And how much water can you trap above
the ground level?
If you are at ground zero,
then simply high minus low, and this is
the water you're trapping.
But, check out this particular unit.
You see that you have a wall of height
two on the left, and you have a wall of
height two on the right.
But, can you trap two units over here?
No, because this building already has a
height of one.
So, how much water you can trap?
Whatever is the minimum height out of
left and right,
minus your current height.
Once again, check out this particular
location. Your left has a height of two,
and your maximum height on the right is
three.
But, can you trap all of this? No.
You have a left height of two, and right
height of three.
You will only be able to trap the
minimum of these. So, you can trap a
maximum of two units.
But, you're already elevated one unit.
So, for this particular block, you can
only trap one unit.
And that is the building block of this
particular question.
Instead of looking at areas, you need to
look at each of these individual units,
and try to determine how much water can
I trap in each of these individual
units.
It could be zero, it could be anything.
And then you just add all of them.
So, this is what we have right now.
We are finding out the water at i-th
location. And i-th location is each
element in my array.
And how do you find it?
You find the minimum of
maximum of left and maximum of right.
What does this mean?
For example, when I am standing at this
particular location,
what is the maximum height I can find on
left? This is my maximum height.
And what is the maximum height I can
find on right? This is a maximum height.
So, maximum left is one and maximum
right is two.
I want the minimum of these. This.
So, I get this and minus the current
height.
The height is zero, so I trap one unit
of water here.
Notice what happens for this particular
condition.
I'm finding out the water at I.
So, what is the maximum of left?
On the left, I don't have any value that
is higher than two.
So, this becomes zero.
And on the right, do I have a maximum
value?
So, on the right, I have a value of
three. So, max right is three, but
minimum of these is zero.
So, if this is zero, I cannot trap any
water.
And that's it.
That is what I'm seeing. I'm not able to
trap any water here.
That is how you have to go on for each
and every location.
But where are stacks coming into the
picture?
If you have already noticed, and if
you're observant enough, how do you find
out the max left and max right?
What are actually max left and max
right?
These are the next greater elements
towards the left and next greater
elements towards the right.
So, when you're looking from over here,
what will you find out? For each
location, you are finding out the max
right.
I have evaluated the max right for each
of the indexes.
And this happened in order of n time.
How about finding out the max left?
This time you have to solve the same
problem, but you're looking at this
particular direction.
And this is simply you want to iterate
from this direction and keep a monotonic
stack.
So, you are just solving the same
problem twice. You're looking from the
left and now you're looking from the
right. So, what do you have now? You
have the max left for each of these
indices and you have the max right for
each of these indices.
Now, what is left? You just have to
apply this formula at each index and
find out the total water.
Notice that if any of the value is zero,
you can simply discard it because if you
are not having any wall, then you cannot
trap any water.
So, some of the indices will just simply
rule out.
Because in all of these, one of the
element is zero.
And how many are we remaining with?
Notice that wherever we have water,
we have some value for left and right.
To find the total water, calculate all
of these values.
Now, you have everything and I will
leave the last part to you as an
exercise. You notice how we can use the
stack data structure in so many
different places, especially a monotonic
stack. This way you're ensuring your
stack has always greater elements or
smaller elements.
And the concept of a next greater
element can be used at a lot of
different places.
Just tell me in the comment section
below where all have you found this
particular concept being used. This will
become a very good collection and I
would also love to discuss all of this.
As a reminder, if you found this video
helpful, please do consider subscribing
to my channel and share this video with
your friends. This really keeps me
motivated and I can make more such
videos. Also, a huge shout out to all of
the members who support my channel. You
guys really keep me going. And as a
member, you do get priority reply to
your comments and early access to new
videos as well.
Also, remember you can now schedule a
one-to-one session with me and we can
chat about anything.
Stay tuned for my upcoming video. Until
then, see you.